Marion Walton
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Marion Walton papers
1915-1976
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Walton, Marion
0.8 linear feet
This small collection of the papers of sculptor Marion Walton measures 0.8 linear feet and dates from 1915-1976. Fifteen folders of letters written to Marion and her mother Blanche Wetherill Walton include many from artists and photographers, writers, musicians and composers, and political figures. Also found are printed materials, photographs, and a file concerning a reception for author Jonathan Daniels.
Provenance
The Marion Walton papers were donated in 1976 by Marion Walton.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Marion Walton was born in 1905 in New Rochelle, New York, the daughter of Ernest Forster Walton and music patron Blanche Wetherill Walton. During the 1920s, she studied at the Art Students League and, from approximately 1922 to 1924, at the Académie de la Grande Chaumière in Paris under sculptor Antoine Bourdelle. One of her classmates was Alberto Giacometti.
In 1933, Walton had a solo exhibition at the Weyhe Gallery and later participated in numerous group exhibitions primarily in New York City and in Paris, France. Her work is represented in private collections in the United States and abroad, and in the museum of the University of Nebraska.
Walton taught students in her studio in New York City and at Sarah Lawrence College. She was also a member of Artists Equity and a charter member of the Sculptors Guild.
Walton was married to James Putnam, assistant to the President of the publishing house, MacMillan Company.
Marion Walton died in 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 0.8 linear feet, dates from 1915-1976, and documents the career of sculptor Marion Walton. Found within the papers are letters, printed material, photographs, and a file concerning a reception for author Jonathan Daniels.
Letters include those received by Walton and her mother, music patron Blanche Wetherill Walton, from many notable correspondents, including artist Charles Green Shaw, historian and suffragist Mary Beard, and novelist Vera Brittain. There are scattered letters from artists Béla Kádár, Rockwell Kent, Fred Dana Marsh, Georgia O'Keeffe, John Singer Sargent, Theo Stamos, and Abbott Handerson Thayer, composers Henry Cowell and Carl Ruggles, musician Pete Seeger, lecturer Ruth Gage-Colby, photographer Roy E. Stryker, political figures James Forrestal, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Shirley Williams, and writers Carl Carmer and Margaret Storm Jameson.
Printed material primarily consists of clippings and exhibition catalogs, and photographs are of Walton, her family, colleagues, and artwork. Of special interest is an early photograph of Alberto Giacometti with Rodin's model Carmen, and a photograph of Pablo Picasso autographed on the reverse.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Daniels, Jonathan, 1902-; Giacometti, Alberto, 1901-1966 -- Photographs; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973 -- Photographs
Subjects-Topical:
Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks
Names:
Shaw, Charles Green, 1892-; Beard, Mary Ritter, 1876-1958; Carmer, Carl Lamson, 1893; Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965; Kadar, Bela; Forrestal, James, 1892-1949; Gage-Colby, Ruth; Jameson, Storm, 1891-1986; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Marsh, Fred Dana, 1872-1961; O'Keefe, Georgia, 1887-1986; Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Stamos, Theodoros, 1922-; Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Walton, Blanche Wetherill; Williams, Shirley, 1930
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series. All series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Letters, 1922-1976 (Box 1; 15 folders)
Series 2: File Concerning a Reception for Jonathan Daniels, 1946 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1924-1976 (Boxes 1-2; 17 folders)
Series 4: Photographs, 1915-1972 (Box 2; 18 folders)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letters, 1922-1976, Series 1:; (Box 1; 15 folders)
  This series contains letters received primarily by Walton and her mother, Blanche Wetherill Walton, from friends and colleagues including artist Charles Green Shaw, historian and suffragist Mary Beard, and novelist Vera Brittain. There are scattered letters from artists Béla Kádár, Rockwell Kent, Fred Dana Marsh, Georgia O'Keeffe, John Singer Sargent, Theo Stamos, and Abbott Handerson Thayer, composers Henry Cowell and Carl Ruggles, musician Pete Seeger, lecturer Ruth Gage-Colby, photographer Roy E. Stryker, political figures James Forrestal, Eleanor Roosevelt, and Shirley Williams, and writers Carl Carmer and Margaret Storm Jameson.
  - Letters, Surnames "A-Z," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1 (hol), Folder 1-2)
  - Letters, 1922-1929 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1932-1933 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1934-1938 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1940, (2 folders) (Box 1 (hol), Folder 6-7)
  - Letters, 1941-1942 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1943-1945 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Letters, 1946 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Letters, 1947-1948 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Letters, 1950-1957 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Letters, 1960-1966 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Letters, 1967 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Letters, 1970-1976 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 15)
- File Concerning a Reception for Jonathan Daniels, 1946, Series 2:; (Box 1; 14 folders)
  This file contains address lists of invitees and their letters of response for a reception to honor Jonathan Daniels, author of Frontier on the Potomac. The event took place on October 22, 1946, and was organized by Walton's husband, James Putnam, for the MacMillan Company publishing house. Among the responses, primarily from politicians and publishers, are letters signed by Bernard Baruch, Felix Frankfurter, J. Edgar Hoover, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Estes Kefauver.
  - Address Lists, 1946 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Letters in Response to the Invitation, 1946, (13 folders) (Box 1 (hol), Folder 17-29)
- Printed Material, 1924-1976, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 17 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Walton and others, a program for a concert in tribute to Walton's mother, and a book about and autographed by Walton's art professor Antoine Bourdelle. A 1939 Sculptors Guild exhibition catalog is autographed by 18 artists including Saul Baizerman, Jose De Creeft, Dorothea Greenbaum, Chaim Gross, and William Zorach.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1 (hol), Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1926-1933 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 31)
  - Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 32)
  - Clippings, 1940 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 33)
  - Clippings, 1941-1947 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1959-1976 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, undated (Box 1 (hol), Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1933-1939 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 37)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1940-1941 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1962 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1964-1967 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1968 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 41)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1970-1972 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Walton, 1973-1976 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 43)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1933-1975 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 44)
  - Program for a Concert in Tribute to Blanche Walton, 1959 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 45)
  - Book, L'Essor Pathétique de Bourdelle, 1924 (Box 1 (hol), Folder 46)
- Photographs, 1915-1972, Series 4:; (Box 2; 18 folders)
  Photographs are of Marion Walton, her family, and colleagues including French actress Danielle Delorme, composer Carl Ruggles, writers Carl Carmer and J. E. Spingarn, artists Gladys Thayer Reasoner and Alberto Giacometti with Rodin's model Carmen, and works of art. There is a photograph of a party at the Art Students League, and a commercially produced photograph of Antoine Bourdelle with Auguste Rodin. There is also a photograph by L. Yvroud of Pablo Picasso standing next to his sculpture L'Homme au Mouton in the town square of French rivera town Vallauris Golfe-Juan. The reverse of this photograph is stamped "Parti Communiste Français" by the photographer and autographed in pencil by Picasso. Travel photographs show views of Greece, Italy, and France, including the town of Vallauris where Walton studied pottery near Picasso's home.
  - Photographs of Marion Walton, 1918-1935 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Marion Walton, 1954-1971 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Family Members, 1915-1961 (Box 2 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Artists, 1921-1972, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 4-6)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Walton, 1933, undated, (11 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Folder 7-17)
  - Travel Photographs, 1951-1953, undated (Box 2 (hol), Folder 18)